so when a program generates a virtual
address for example does a load or a
store to it the processor needs to
access some physical address the
question is how does the processor map
what the program is trying to access to
what really should be accessed this
mapping would be really hard if every
bite of virtual memory could map to an
arbitrary bite in the physical memory
then we would basically have to have a
huge table of mappings and we don't want
to do do that cuz that table would be
very large and consume a lot of our
memory so instead the program's memory
is divided into equal size chunks called
Pages a typical page size is 4 kiloby so
this would be page zero in this program
page one in this program page two 3 4
Etc so pretty much the first 4 kilobytes
will be page zero the next 4 kilobytes
will be page one and and so on note that
each page is aligned to the page size so
the page for example is 4 kiloby and it
begins at a 4 kilobyte boundary so this
is our virtual memory our physical
memory is divided into slots that can
hold pages and these slots are called
frames so if you remember your caches
pretty much the physical memory behaves
like a cache for the virtual memory in
that it has a certain number of places
where we can put
pages so a page is kind of like a memory
block and the frame is kind of like a
cach line except that this is the actual
memory we have and this is the memory
that the program just thinks it has but
we never actually have that memory so
now the operating system creates a
mapping where it decides which pages in
the program will map to which frames we
can do something like this for example
so page zero for example the operating
system decides to put it in frame zero
page one can be in frame two page two
can be in frame three if we have another
process it has its own page zero page
one Etc and these Pages might map to
different frames if we want this page
one and this page one to be the same
because these two processes needs to
share memory then we can map them to the
same
frame and now when this processor writes
to its memory
and this processor reads to the same
address they actually are accessing the
same memory location so this process
reads what this process
wrote but for page zero for example they
have different memory there so this
process sees its own content for page
zero and this process sees its own
content for page zero so who
decides how to do this mapping here and
here and the answer is the operating
system design
and the actual mapping mechanism is
called a page table it's a table that
says for each page in a process where is
that page really mapped in the physical
memory this is the page table for this
process another process with its own
idea of virtual memory will have a
different page table that says for each
page here where does it go here